Alright בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is מ"ו Mem Vav
46. We pick up at the bottom of מ"ה עמוד ב'. Mem
Hey Amud Bais. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Shmuel, it is three lines before the lines get wide, eight lines
from the bottom of the page. And we actually start a new,
obviously related discussion, but a new discussion now that we've discussed the
מצוה mitzvah of לולב lulav
in the מקדש, Mikdash, out of the מקדש, Mikdash, on שבת, Shabbat,
the מצוה mitzvah of ערבה aravah in the מקדש, Mikdash, out of
the מקדש, Mikdash, the special status of שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, and
we had very beautiful אגדתא Aggadeta yesterday once again connecting the idea
of the לולב lulav to a קרבן, korban, which is a very
interesting and repeated theme. And now we pick up with a discussion,
sort of taking a step back and discussing an important question that
we have not really addressed until now, which is the issue of
ברכה, bracha, and looking specifically at לולב lulav and at סוכה, sukkah,
but then we're going to also circle back to discuss ערבה aravah
as well. Let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar
Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel. So says רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the
name of שמואל. Shmuel.
לולב שבעה וסוכה יום אחד. Lulav shiva ve-sukkah yom echad.
לולב Lulav is seven and סוכה sukkah is only one day. Does
not mean you only sit in a סוכה sukkah one day, it's
a question of the ברכה. bracha. You make the ברכה bracha on
the לולב lulav every day of the seven days, אשר קדשנו במצותיו
וצונו על נטילת לולב, asher kidishanu be-mitzvotav ve-tzivanu al netilat lulav, which
is in itself a חידוש chiddush because the other days are not
biblical, so no, not time the בית, Beit, well we'll see, but
presumably not. And סוכה sukkah only one day, which is bizarre because
סוכה sukkah is biblical, you're sitting in it every day. What is
the logic that you would only make, according to this, obviously you
know this is not the הלכה, halacha, but what is the logic?
The logic is that the מצוה mitzvah סוכה sukkah is not—we tend
to conceptualize the מצוה mitzvah סוכה sukkah as individual acts. The act
of eating this amount of bread or whatever it is must be
done in the סוכה. sukkah. So we say, 'Ah, we're going back
into the סוכה sukkah again, we have to make another ברכה, bracha,
we're doing another act.' But actually conceptually the act of סוכה sukkah
is one act. בסכות תשבו שבעת ימים, Basukkot teshvu shivat yamim, dwelling
in the סוכה sukkah for the entire week. So when you start,
when you move into the סוכה sukkah and you start your dwelling,
you make the ברכה bracha and then for the remainder of the
week it's a continuation, it's all part of the same act of
dwelling. The fact that every now and then you step out of
the סוכה, sukkah, okay, you step out of your house too, as
I've said when we learned earlier פרקים, perakim, it's not a jail,
but the whole week is a continuation of the one act of
living in the סוכה sukkah for the week. Again, for us the
reality is a little different, but conceptually that is the nature of
the מצוה. mitzvah. So he says you make one ברכה bracha on
סוכה, sukkah, that actually makes a lot of sense if you think
about conceptually what the מצוה mitzvah of סוכה sukkah is. One minute.
וגמר... Ve-gamar... so the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל לולב שבעה וסוכה יום אחד. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel
lulav shiva ve-sukkah yom echad. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what is the
reason?
לולב דמפסיק לילות מימים, Lulav de-mafsik leilayout mi-yamim, לולב lulav the nights
divide the day, the מצוה mitzvah of לולב lulav does not apply
at night, so כל יומא מצוה בפני עצמיה הוא, kol yoma mitzvah
bafne atzmei hu, every day is a separate מצוה, mitzvah, it's a
separate act of taking the לולב lulav each day. It's not one
process. First of all it's not one process because each thing is
a distinct act, and the evidence that it's not one process is
that it doesn't apply at night, so obviously you cannot conceive of
it as a continuous process.
However, סוכה דלא מפסיק לילות מימים, sukkah de-lo mafsik leilayout mi-yamim, סוכה
sukkah where the nights do not interrupt the days, כולהו שבעה כחד
יומא אריכתא דמו, kulu shiva ke-chad yoma arichta damu, it's all seven
as one long day, and also as I've just got through saying,
it's not like there's a distinct act like shaking the לולב, lulav,
it's just the continuous process of dwelling in the סוכה, sukkah, which
is an uninterrupted process, and therefore it is one ברכה bracha at
the beginning. Very nice logical idea reflecting what at least conceptually reality
of sitting in the סוכה sukkah is. One minute. ורבה בר בר
חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Ve-Rabba bar Bar Chana Amar Rebi Yochanan, so
that's a statement in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. Now here's the
statement of רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar Bar Chana in the
name of רבי יוחנן. Rebi Yochanan. סוכה שבעה ולולב יום אחד. Sukkah
shiva ve-lulav yom echad. Just to make things fun, it's the exact
opposite. סוכה Sukkah is seven days and לולב lulav is one day.
מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? סוכה דאורייתא שבעה, Sukkah de-oraita
shiva, because every day סוכה sukkah is a biblical מצוה, mitzvah, so
it gets its own ברכה. bracha. לולב דרבנן סגי ליה בחד יומא,
Lulav de-rabanan sagi lei be-chad yoma, and לולב lulav is rabbinic, it's
enough for one day. Enough for one day is a funny way
of saying it, maybe a more precise way of saying it is
the first day is the only day that's biblical, it's the only
day you are able to say אשר קדשנו במצותיו, asher kidishanu be-mitzvotav,
right? Meaning סגי ליה בחד יומא sagi lei be-chad yoma means let's
say I missed the first day of לולב, lulav, would I make
a ברכה bracha the second day? Presumably not. It's not saying one
is enough, it's saying you're only entitled and obligated to make it
on the first day which is biblical. So this position says you
only make the ברכה bracha on the biblical day, so for לולב
lulav that's day one, and for סוכה sukkah it's all seven days.
How about this idea of a continuous process? That doesn't impress him.
Every day still, you know, you have to acknowledge that each day
you're continuing to do the מצוה, mitzvah, each day you make a
separate ברכה. bracha. Yes, Michael, question?
I thought it's eight things that he's saying seven days, because like
our משנה Mishnah was saying, even לולב lulav can be six or
seven.
Yeah, yeah, we're not... no, exactly. Okay, yeah, yes.
It's so according to that if
you were to say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו asher kidishanu be-mitzvotav ve-tzivanu
like you do on the other days of It's
so according to that, if you were to say אשר קדשנו במצותיו
וצונו Asher Kiddishanu Bemitzvosav Vitzivanu like you do on the other days
of סוכות, Sukkot, you'd be making the same mistake as saying that
ברכה Bracha like on חנוכה Hanukkah or on פורים, Purim, that is
to say, like a...
Well, we're going to get to that. We're going to get to
how we can make לולב Lulav the other days, which is our
practice, and it is based on this idea that yes, we make
ברכות Brachot on דרבנן DeRabbanan מצוות. Mitzvot. Okay, so we will get
to that, but for now, one level of the debate is can
you make a ברכה Bracha on the days that are דרבנן. DeRabbanan.
The other question is סוכה, Sukkah, which conceptually is a continuous process,
one ברכה Bracha should be sufficient, and here's an idea, well maybe
still you should make it on each day separately. Now why exactly
to make it on each day separately, if the logic is that
one day is sufficient, could just very well be that, you know,
at the experiential level, you know, each day, if you made it
five days ago, you know, you're not really marking it, you know,
as a מצוה Mitzvah to yourself, which is what the ברכה Bracha
is. Five days ago you made the ברכה Bracha on סוכה. Sukkah.
So each day you want to sort of acknowledge it as a
separate, and you know, each day acknowledge it again. But the logic
is very powerful in terms of the position of רב יהודה אמר
שמואל. Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel. Well, let's continue to see how this
develops. Okay, so those are three positions, they're mirror images of one
another. Okay. כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki Ata Ravin Amar
Rabbi Yochanan, when רבין Ravin came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he
had a different version in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
אחד זה ואחד זה שבע. Echad Zeh Ve'echad Zeh Sheva. Each one
you make seven days. Seven days for לולב, Lulav, it doesn't matter
that it's דרבנן, DeRabbanan, each day is on the other days, each
day is distinct. And seven days for סוכה, Sukkah, because each day
is דאורייתא, De'oraita, and again, the idea that in some conceptual level
they're not distinct doesn't matter. So each one you make it on
every single day. Of course there's a logical fourth possibility, which is
each one you make it only once. You make it once for
לולב Lulav because it's only biblical the first day, once for סוכה
Sukkah because it's a continuous מצוה. Mitzvah. But that we're not having.
So we have three out of the four logical possibilities. Okay. אמר
רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, obviously the last one is our practice,
although again, in the גמרא, Gemara, the idea that you make it
all seven presumably means once a day by סוכה, Sukkah, which is
not our practice. Our practice by סוכה, Sukkah, you make the ברכה
Bracha whenever you go in afresh to do a new act of
living, which for us, we don't, since we tend not to sleep
in a סוכה, Sukkah, is defined as eating a minimum amount of
food that is obligated in a סוכה. Sukkah. So for us we
might make it five times one day and zero times the next
day. Right, so we really don't do either of these, we do
it for סוכה Sukkah every, we treat סוכה Sukkah like the idea
of לולב, Lulav, like this idea of a distinct act of shaking
the לולב, Lulav, so there's distinct acts of sitting in a סוכה,
Sukkah, and every time we do a distinct act we make a
ברכה. Bracha. If you take a look at what תוספות Tosafot says,
אחד זה ואחד זה שבע. Echad Zeh Ve'echad Zeh Sheva.
Okay, if you see this little תוספות, Tosafot, he says אין סוכה
ולולב שוים לברכה, Ein Sukkah Velulav Shavim Levracha, that לולב אינו מברך
אלא פעם אחת ביום. Lulav Eino Mevarech Ela Pa'am Achat Bayom. לולב
Lulav you do it once in the day because it's one act
and then you're done. אבל סוכה כל אימת דנכנס לה, Aval Sukkah
Kol Eimat Denichnas Lah, every time you go into it, כדי שיאכל
וישב וישן, Kedei Sheyochal Veyishev Veyishan, he also, he still had sleeping
in the סוכה. Sukkah. ואפילו עשר פעמים ביום מברך על כל אחת
ואחת. Ve'afilu Eser Pe'amim Bayom Mevarech Al Kol Achat Ve'achat.
Okay, and then it's sort of like תפילין Tefillin that every time
you put it on again on the same day you would make
another ברכה. Bracha. Okay, and then, so base, so
but that is not clear in the גמרא. Gemara. In the גמרא
Gemara again that is starting to, you know, like turn the act
of סוכה Sukkah from a process into discrete acts of, an act
of this eating, that act of eating, and then for him it's
like making a ברכה Bracha on every discrete act. In the גמרא
Gemara you don't have it yet. In the גמרא Gemara you have
the idea that סוכה Sukkah is a continuous act of all seven
days, and that's the opinion that you make it only once at
the beginning. And presumably the opinion that you make it each day
is that, yes, I can see that it's a continuous act, but
you know, a continuous act, you know, it loses its framing, so
you want to re-sort of acknowledge it, you know, on a daily
basis and relabel it, but still conceptually it's a continuous act. So
in the גמרא Gemara you have the idea of making it daily
or making it once, but in our practice we've transformed this thing
which is conceptually a continuous act, we've transformed it into discrete acts,
and therefore for us we wind up making it with every discrete
act. But that is not stated in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so
what do we have now in the גמרא? Gemara? You have the
question, meaning you know, you have the idea one and seven, seven
and one, seven and seven, but it boils down to the question
by לולב Lulav of do you make it only on the biblical
day, day one, or you make it on all the days even
the rabbinic days, all seven days? And by סוכה Sukkah the question
is is it a continuous act and you only make it at
the beginning or the way I would phrase it is even if
it's a continuous act you need to relabel it on a daily
basis? Those are what the issues are about. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, נחוט הדין
דרבה בר בר חנה
בידך, Nechot Hadin Derabba Bar Bar Chana Beyadecha, take hold of the
position of רבה בר בר חנה Rabba Bar Bar Chana that said
seven days for סוכה Sukkah and one day for לולב. Lulav. Take
hold of it in your hand. דכולי אמוראי קיימי כוותיה, Dekulei Amorai
Kaymi Kevateih, all the אמוראים Amoraim agree with this. So according to
this the claim is that there was a consensus of
seven
days of סוכה Sukkah but only one day for a ברכה Bracha
on לולב. Lulav. Obviously that is not our actual פסק, Psak, but
he's saying that should be your... position. That's the consensus.
So דכולי אמוראי קיימי כוותיה בסוכה, D’kulei Amorai kaimei kevataih b’Sukkah, that
at least by סוכה Sukkah the idea that there's seven days by
סוכה, Sukkah, as that there's the consensus of. Okay, and therefore at
least minimally by סוכה Sukkah the idea of making it on a
daily basis, but presumably he's saying even the idea of לולב Lulav
should really only be one day, one day.
Okay, מיתיבי, Meiseiv, I'll ask you on this. Top of מ"ו ע"א.
mem vav amud aleph. העושה לולב לעצמו, Ha’oseh Lulav l’atzmo, so here
we have a תוספתא, Tosefta, somebody is constructing a לולב Lulav for
themselves. אומר, Omer, you're not like in the business and constructing a
million לולבים, Lulavim, you're constructing the לולב Lulav that you're going to
use for the מצוה. Mitzvah. It could be a week before, it
could be... yeah, you're binding, exactly, you're binding the הדסים hadassim and
the ערבות aravos together, correct, even if לולב אין צריך אגד, Lulav
ein tzarich eged, nevertheless that was certainly the practice. So you're basically
involving yourself in constructing and putting together the לולב. Lulav. So אומר
ברוך שהחיינו וקיימנו והגיענו לזמן הזה. Omer baruch shehecheyanu v’kiyimanu v’higianu lazman
hazeh. You say a שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu. Now this is an important הלכה
Halacha that most people are not aware of, which is there are
two aspects of שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on the ימים טובים. Yamim Tovim. There's
the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu that we say that relates to the fact that
it's יום טוב, Yom Tov, the קדושת היום, kedushas hayom, which is
the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu we say at קידוש. Kiddush. There's also a שהחיינו
Shehecheyanu we say about the new מצוות Mitzvos that we're doing. So
for example, you say a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu at the night of סוכות
Sukkos because of קידוש Kiddush because it's a new חג, Chag, and
then you say it again when you take the לולב Lulav because
that's the new מצוה Mitzvah of, it's a periodic מצוה Mitzvah and
you make a שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu. Now this actually is interesting because what
happens the second day of סוכות? Sukkos? Do you make a שהחיינו
Shehecheyanu and קידוש Kiddush the second day of סוכות? Sukkos? There's a
pop quiz. Yes, you do. You do. Okay, I'm not discussing reversing
the order about that. Yes, you do. Do you make a שהחיינו
Shehecheyanu when you take the לולב Lulav the second day? No. Why
not? Because here's the difference. The שהחיינו Shehecheyanu of the sanctity of
יום טוב Yom Tov is one that is made not in anticipation
of יום טוב, Yom Tov, it's one that is made because to
actually sort of sanctify the day as when the sanctity of יום
טוב Yom Tov actually is present, when the day actually begins. So
on the second day of יום טוב, Yom Tov, you have to
say, look, doing this whole idea as if we don't know what
day is יום טוב, Yom Tov, ספיקא דיומא. Sfeika d'yoma. If yesterday
wasn't really יום טוב, Yom Tov, then the ברכה שהחיינו Bracha Shehecheyanu
I made doesn't do any good, that was a, that was a
weekday. Today is really only the day that is יום טוב, Yom
Tov, so today demands a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu and that's why you make
a second שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on the second night. But when it comes
to לולב, Lulav, let's go through the same process. Okay, so let's
say, so I made שהחיינו Shehecheyanu yesterday, but let's say yesterday wasn't
really יום טוב, Yom Tov, let's say today is really the first
day of סוכות. Sukkos. Okay, but you know what? The שהחיינו Shehecheyanu
you make on the new מצוה Mitzvah is not limited to the
doing of the מצוה, Mitzvah, it can be made as soon as
you begin to engage yourself in the מצוה. Mitzvah. For example, if
I buy a new suit, I can make the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu when
I buy the suit, and I can make the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu when
I first put it on, because basically it's encountering this new thing
and therefore it is, it could be at various stages when that
encounter begins. It could be early, but if I miss the early
stage, it could be at another more, at another more meaningful stage.
So therefore even if I didn't yet do the מצוה Mitzvah yesterday
because yesterday was theoretically still a weekday in this idea of ספיקא
דיומא, Sfeika d'yoma, I was beginning my involvement in the מצוה, Mitzvah,
and therefore that שהחיינו Shehecheyanu counts. So if I made the שהחיינו
Shehecheyanu when I bought the suit, I don't make a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu
when I wear the suit. And if I made the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu
yesterday, I don't have to make it today even though today is
the first I am actually doing the מצוה. Mitzvah. Which is why
the תוספתא Tosefta says that the real first time you should be
making the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on the לולב Lulav is not when you're
planning on taking it, but when you're getting it ready and when
you're constructing it. And we don't, we don't do that, but that's
what the תוספתא Tosefta says.
העושה לולב לעצמו, Ha’oseh Lulav l’atzmo, you say שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu. העושה סוכה
לעצמו, Ha’oseh Sukkah l’atzmo,
you say a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu and so on. Okay, and that is
because, by the way, and this is complicated, it refers to what
Michael's going to say but I'm not going to unpack it right
now, the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu we say on סוכות Sukkos night is a
double duty. It's for the חג Chag and it's for the first
beginning of the מצוה Mitzvah of סוכה. Sukkah. And that has to
do with why we switch the order first night, second night, but
that could be a little assignment for homework you can figure that
one out. Okay, but anyway it is interesting, but we're not going
to go into that. Okay, but there are two aspects of שהחיינו,
Shehecheyanu, for the חג Chag and for the מצוה. Mitzvah. And what
this ברייתא Braisa is saying is the מצוה שהחיינו, Mitzvah Shehecheyanu, the
חג שהחיינו Chag Shehecheyanu have to wait for the חג, Chag, but
the מצוה שהחיינו Mitzvah Shehecheyanu can begin as soon as you encounter
the מצוה Mitzvah and therefore you can make it as soon as
you're constructing the לולב. Lulav. If you would have made the שהחיינו
Shehecheyanu when you constructed the לולב, Lulav, then when you came to
take the לולב Lulav on the first day you would not say
שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu, you would only say אשר קדשנו במצותיו. asher kiddishanu b'mitzvosav.
Okay, so that's the underlying principle and assumption of this, of this
תוספתא, Tosefta, yes.
A lot of lighting of יום טוב Yom Tov candles before it's
actually
חג, Chag, but
that would seem by that to be a little early to be
reciting...
Well, all first of all the lighting of candles is seen as
the bringing in of the חג, Chag, so if you do a,
if you start a יום טוב Yom Tov early, which you allowed
to do, you know, you can make the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu in the
קידוש Kiddush early as well. So that's yeah, so that's different.
Although our custom is to wait until it's actually dark before making
קידוש Kiddush in the סוכה. Sukkah.
Yeah, but whatever. There're other reasons behind that, but yes. But in
principle that, you know, the חג Chag starts earlier. Also raises questions
about whether the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on
the—let's just leave it at that for now. Yeah.
Why do we make a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu before eating מצה? Matzah?
Oh, so that's a good—that's a question in general, you know, and
why don't we—and there are other questions about certain ברכות Brachot בליל
סדר. b'Leil Seder. Why don't we make the ברכה Bracha for—why don't
we make a ברכה Bracha on מגיד Maggid בליל סדר b'Leil Seder
and so on? So for the מצה Matzah issue at least let's
just say a simple answer right now might be that, similar to
the point of—of סוכה, Sukkah, that it does double duty. The שהחיינו
Shehecheyanu that we make on the—on the יום טוב Yom Tov for
ליל סדר Leil Seder on the קידוש Kiddush also relates to the
מצה Matzah that we're about to be eating as well. It's sort
of like העושה לולב לעצמו, ha'oseh lulav l'atzmo, you say a שהחיינו,
Shehecheyanu, so here you're getting ready to be eating the מצה, Matzah,
you say the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu even though it wasn't a second before
you actually ate that מצה. Matzah. Okay.
So even if I bake מצה Matzah I could actually make שהחיינו
Shehecheyanu on baking it?
I'm not—I'm giving you the basic parameters. We're not פסקן-ing. pasken Let's
move on. The גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So now—so let's
read that again. העושה לולב לעצמו אומר ברוך שהחיינו וקיימנו והגיענו לזמן
הזה. ha'oseh lulav l'atzmo omer baruch Shehecheyanu v'kiyimanu v'higiyanu lazman hazeh. נטלו
לצאת בו, natlo latzet bo, then when it finally comes time to
be יוצא, yotzei, אומר ברוך אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על נטילת לולב.
omer baruch asher kidshanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu al netilat lulav. You say the
ברכה Bracha of על נטילת לולב. al netilat lulav. Okay. ואף על
פי שבירך עליו—now v'af al pi shebeirach alav that was very interesting,
just the idea of the two separate ברכות. Brachot. Now we get
to our question about when you make those ברכות. Brachot. ואף על
פי שבירך עליו יום ראשון, v'af al pi shebeirach alav yom rishon,
even though you made the ברכה Bracha on לולב Lulav the first
day, חוזר ומברך כל שבעה, chozer umevarech kol shivah, you make it
all seven days. Okay. So number one, as opposed to what was
just said a minute ago that you should only be making it
one day, here it tells you make it all seven days. Number
two, העושה סוכה לעצמו, ha'oseh sukkah l'atzmo, when you begin making the
סוכה, Sukkah, אומר ברוך שהחיינו וקיימנו והגיענו לזמן הזה, omer baruch Shehecheyanu
v'kiyimanu v'higiyanu lazman hazeh, again you make a שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu. Okay. נכנס
לישב בה,
nichnas
leishaiv bah, once you start—once you begin—go in there to do the
first מצוה, mitzvah, אומר אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לישב בסוכה.
omer asher kidshanu
b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu leishev basukkah. וכיון—and v'keivan now here's the clincher or the
critical line for us, וכיון שבירך יום ראשון, v'keivan shebeirach yom rishon,
once you made the ברכה Bracha on the first day, שוב אינו
מברך, shuv eino mevarech, you don't make it any other days. So
here it's an explicit ברייתא, braita, which is the exact opposite of
what the גמרא Gemara just said is what we should adopt as
our position. It says seven days for לולב Lulav and one day
for סוכה. Sukkah. So קשיא לולב אלולב קשיא סוכה אסוכה, kashya lulav
a'lulav kashya sukkah a'sukkah, it contradicts the earlier position on both levels,
the לולב Lulav position and the סוכה Sukkah position. So בשלמא לולב
אלולב לא קשיא, bishlama lulav a'lulav lo kashya, so the contradiction of
לולב, Lulav, where we had said before one day and this is
saying seven days, that doesn't have to be seen as a contradiction.
Why? Because כאן בזמן שבית המקדש קיים כאן בזמן שאין בית המקדש
קיים. kan bizman sheBeit HaMikdash kayam, kan bizman she'ein Beit HaMikdash kayam.
It matters whether there's a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash or not. We
said one day. Why do we say only one day by לולב?
Lulav? Because the other days were דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Well, maybe this ברייתא
braita that says all seven days is assuming that it's at the
time of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and רש״י Rashi adds and
assuming you're going to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and doing the
מצוה mitzvah there. So then it's biblical all seven days. So we
could live with the idea that this says seven days for לולב.
Lulav. This ברייתא braita maybe assumes that it's—that it's in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash and it's dealing with a context of being in
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and it's biblical each day. אלא סוכה
אסוכה קשיא, ella sukkah a'sukkah kashya, but we really got a problem
because we said סוכה Sukkah all seven days and this ברייתא braita
says סוכה Sukkah is only one day—one day, the beginning. So which
is it? So the גמרא Gemara says תנאי היא. tannai hee. You
know what? You're right. I can see the point that this question
of doing it once at the beginning of the process or doing
it every day is a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. And therefore, yes,
what we was quoting before as an אמורא, Amora, a debate of
אמוראים, Amoraim, actually is rooted in a תנאי Tannaitic debate. This ברייתא,
braita, you're right, says once at the beginning, but I'm going to
show you a תנא Tanna that says that logically that you could
make it every day or that would say a position we're going
to see by תפילין tefillin that logically could be applied here that
would indicate you make it every day. Let's take a look. דתניא,
detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braita: תפילין. tefillin. You're putting—you're wearing
תפילין. tefillin. כל זמן שמניחן מברך עליהם דברי רבי. kol zman shemenichan
mevarech aleihem divrei Rabbi. רבי Rabbi says whenever you put them on,
even if you put them on multiple times in a day, you
make the ברכה Bracha each time. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, and the
חכמים Chachamim say, אינו מברך אלא שחרית בלבד. eino mevarech ella shacharit
bilvad. You only make the ברכה Bracha once, and after that it's
a continuous process of wearing תפילין. tefillin. So, yeah, and therefore presumably
what the רבנן Rabbanan are saying here is that even if you
take it off and put it on
again—well, we'll talk about going to the bathroom in a minute—it is
not a new act, it's still part of the same continuous process,
and therefore one ברכה Bracha for something that is done not one
discrete time. You lift up your לולב, Lulav, you put it down.
That you do—do it each day separately. But something that is a
continuous process—wearing תפילין tefillin is a continuous
process—then you are only going to be one ברכה Bracha per day.
Okay. Now Which one here supports the idea that you go make
a ברכה Bracha on the סוכה Sukkah right each day? So if
it's not the position that says one ברכה Bracha on תפילין Tefillin
a day, although that would seem to be parallel. One ברכה Bracha
on תפילין Tefillin a day, one ברכה Bracha on סוכה Sukkah day.
No. Because by תפילין Tefillin the reason you make it once a
day is because nighttime is not a time for תפילין. Tefillin. So
every day is distinct. So that, but in principle, that idea of
making it once a day for תפילין Tefillin is really saying you
make it once at the beginning of the process and you never
make it again during that process. By תפילין Tefillin the process ends
after, at nightfall. By סוכה Sukkah the process ends at the end
of seven days. But that position by תפילין Tefillin is once for
the whole process. So that would be the position once for the
week for סוכה. Sukkah. The second position, however, says although it is
a process, there are distinct times you make the ברכה. Bracha. So
by תפילין Tefillin those distinct times would be every time you put
on תפילין Tefillin again. And now what would it be by סוכה?
Sukkah? So here רש"י Rashi would say, going back to the simple
פשט Pshat reading of the earlier גמרא, Gemara, רש"י Rashi would say
well the distinct times by סוכה Sukkah is let's say, you know,
every morning, once a day, you know, once a day. It's not
really distinct like taking off your תפילין, Tefillin, putting it back on,
but the point being even though it's a process we're going to
acknowledge multiple opportunities to be making a ברכה. Bracha. And by סוכה
Sukkah those multiple opportunities will be once a day. תוספות Tosafot might
say, and this might claim that this גמרא Gemara actually is pointing
us to what our current practice is. Because the same way by
תפילין Tefillin what determines the distinct moments during a process, the distinct
moments in which you're going to make a new ברכה Bracha is
when you do a new act of putting on the תפילין, Tefillin,
even if we conceptualize it as a process. So by סוכה Sukkah
as well, even if it's a seven-day process, the distinct acts of
moving, going back into the סוכה Sukkah to do another act of
eating will be another ברכה. Bracha. So this גמרא Gemara once it,
now that it's moving to תפילין, Tefillin, is a lot closer to
our practice. Okay, so what do you have by תפילין? Tefillin? You
have a debate. The חכמים Chachamim say once a day no matter
how many times you take it off and put it on because
it's a process, so that we do it once for the whole
process, whereas the, whereas the first position, who has the first position?
רבי Rebbi says even though it's a process there are multiple points
in which you make the ברכה. Bracha. And that the גמרא Gemara
saying as, that's our position of making the ברכה Bracha of סוכה
Sukkah multiple times. Either daily or multiple times every time you go
back to sit in the סוכה Sukkah again. Okay, so that's really
is rooted in this debate of the תנאים. Tannaim. So let's see
now where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
איתמר, Itmar, it was taught. אביי Abaye אמר, amar, הלכה hilcha כרבי
KeRebbi by תפילין, Tefillin, every time you put it on again, and
therefore by סוכה Sukkah every, multiple ברכות Brachos on סוכה. Sukkah. ורבא
VeRava אמר, amar, הלכה hilcha כרבנן, KeRabbanan, no, we rule like the
rabbis just once a day, and maybe he would say by סוכה
Sukkah also once, once for the whole week. אמר רב Amar Rav,
מרי ברה דבת שמואל. breh d'bat Shmuel. So רב מרי Rav Mari
the, the daughter, the son of the daughter of שמואל, Shmuel, interesting,
right,
attributed after his mother although the mother doesn't get a name, she's
only the daughter of שמואל. Shmuel. Anyway, חזינא ליה לרבא, Chazeina lei
leRava, I saw רבא Rava דלא עביד כשמעתיה, delo avid kishmatei, רבא
Rava was not being consistent with his own position because רבא Rava
basically said that we rule like the רבנן Rabbanan and it's once,
once for the whole day. I saw רבא Rava was being inconsistent.
Where was רבא Rava being inconsistent? אלא, Ella, here's what I saw
רבא Rava do. מקדים וקאי ועייל לבית הכסא, Makdim vekai veayil leveit
hakise, he'd get up early, he'd go to the bathroom, ונפיק, venafik,
he'd come out of the bathroom, this on a daily basis, what
he would do, ומשא ידיה, umashi yadei, wash his hands, ומנח תפילין,
umanach tefillin, and then put on תפילין, Tefillin, ומברך. umevarech. So he
made his ברכה Bracha on תפילין Tefillin first thing in the morning.
וכי איצטריך זימנא אחרינא, Vechi itztarich zimna acharina, and then later in
the day, because they would wear תפילין Tefillin throughout the day, that's
also why we're thinking of it also, you know, as a process,
so he had to go to the bathroom later in the day,
עייל לבית הכסא, ayil leveit hakise, he'd go back into the bathroom,
obviously he'd first take off his תפילין, Tefillin, we didn't say that
but that's implicit. ונפיק ומשא ידיה, Venafik umashi yadei, he'd come out
of the bathroom and wash his hands, ומנח תפילין, umanach tefillin, and
he put on תפילין Tefillin again, ומברך, umevarech, and he made another
ברכה. Bracha. So you see even רבא Rava really conceives that you
will make a ברכה Bracha multiple times in the day when you
put it on again and not that it's only once for the
whole process. Now it is worth noting that there's a big difference
between that and the case of תפילין Tefillin or that and just
taking off your תפילין, Tefillin, waiting an hour and putting it back
on. Because actually this is the הלכה, halacha, if you take off
your תפילין Tefillin and then put it back on, you have to
make another ברכה. Bracha. So what's the הלכה? halacha? The הלכה halacha
is you have to make another ברכה Bracha if you took it
off to, for like to be done with it. You weren't, or
you know, not to put it on immediately, and, you know, and
then that would be, then you would make another ברכה. Bracha. But
if you took it off and you were planning on putting it
on right away and you went and put it on right away
again, then actually that would be considered a continuation of the process
and you wouldn't. There needs to be something that actually separates them.
One thing that separates is going to the bathroom. You're not allowed
to have תפילין Tefillin on in the bathroom. So therefore even if
you only needed to go to the bathroom for a second, right?
If I needed to take off my תפילין Tefillin and run out
to the street to, I don't know, get my kid off of
the bus and I came back
in... But if I took it off for a second to go
to the bathroom and I came back, I would make another ברכה.
bracha. Why? Because since you're not allowed to have תפילין tefillin on
in the bathroom, that moment of being in the bathroom is considered
an absolute divider between the previous act and the current act because
there was a period of time where I was not allowed, I
was in a space where I was not allowed to have תפילין.
tefillin. And that way, by the way, תפילין tefillin is different than
טלית. tallis. If I take off my טלית tallis to run to
the bathroom and go to the bathroom and then come back, I
do make another ברכה bracha on- I mean I don't make another
ברכה bracha on טלית. tallis. Because you're allowed to have a טלית
tallis on technically. We don't, it's not
כבוד, kavod, it's not respectful but halakhically, because טלית tallis doesn't have
קדושה, kedusha, it's תשמישי מצוה tashmishei mitzvah not תשמישי קדושה, tashmishei kedusha,
doesn't have God's name in it, you are allowed to have a
טלית tallis in the bathroom. So therefore, you do not make another
ברכה bracha if there's not been a long interruption, but by תפילין
tefillin you do. So, back to this point, רבא Rava made another
ברכה? bracha? Sure, because do we consider it a continuous process or
not? Well, if he was in the bathroom, that broke up the
process. Okay, is that necessarily the same הלכה halakha if you just
סתם stam took it off and took it on? Is that the
same הלכה halakha if you were living in your סוכה sukkah and
you went out for a little while and came back? Maybe not.
Maybe that would be an uninterrupted process. Maybe by- right? So there's
a difference to say you make a new ברכה bracha when you
really break the process that doesn't necessarily prove the story when you
don't break the process. But nevertheless, since that had not been discussed
before, the assumption is that when רבא Rava says once a day,
it means once a day regardless. You will never make it more
than once a day. And here we're saying aha! רבא Rava himself
was not consistent because רבא Rava did make it more than once
a day if he would go to the bathroom in the middle.
So you see the idea that even רבא Rava concedes that once
a day does not always get you off the hook. Okay?
Is it the בית הכסא beit hakisse the issue or the action
of-
no, it actually is the בית הכסא beit hakisse because it was
very smelly and so on, which raises questions nowadays because our bathrooms
are really not halakhic בית הכסא. beit hakisse. Okay, but we're not
going there.
Or if you're- if you're camping.
Yeah, yeah. Okay. Okay, so now but yes, but now this one
we get one more. So anyway, the point is, is it once
for the process or is it multiple times for the process of
תפילין? tefillin? רבא Rava says once. But now the statement is even
רבא Rava was not consistent. Now I pointed out that that's particularly
a moment where the process really was interrupted, but nevertheless, רבא Rava
had said once and here we see that there are times that
רבא Rava himself concedes you make it multiple times. And therefore the
upshot is
ואנן נמי כרבי עבדינא vanan nami k'rebbi avidina and we also follow
רבי, Rebbi, not רבנן. Rabbanan. So by תפילין tefillin we would do
it multiple times. Each time you put on the תפילין tefillin anew,
we would make a new ברכה, bracha, even multiple times in the
same day. ומברכים כל שבעה umevarchim kol shiva and similarly by סוכה,
sukkah, we make a ברכה bracha the entire week, not just once.
Now again, what does the entire week mean? It could mean we
make it once a day like סוכה sukkah like לולב lulav once
a day. That somehow each day is like a new act of
living in the סוכה. sukkah. Each day, you know, in- again, not
that the activity is different, but somehow it just is somewhat distinct
from the previous day. That's what רש"י Rashi means very literally כל
שבעה. kol shiva. תוספות Tosafot's read, which again is much more similar
to the תפילין tefillin idea, is no. When you- for the entire
week, every time you re-enter the סוכה sukkah to do another eating
or another sleeping in the סוכה, sukkah, that's like putting on your
תפילין tefillin again on the same day and that discrete act requires
another ברכה. bracha. Okay, I hope I haven't complicated it too much.
Just to refresh where we're up to. The issue about לולב lulav
at this stage, clearly every day is distinct and every act is
distinct. The only question is you make a ברכה bracha on the
rabbinic days? That's the question by לולב. lulav. By סוכה, sukkah, it's
a- it's a very interesting conceptual question. It's a seven-day process. So
the argument could be once for the whole seven days. Or do
we somehow say that even if it's a seven-day process, we're going
to have multiple ברכות. brachot. And what would that multiple ברכות brachot
be? רש"י Rashi understands it means one ברכה bracha a day, one
ברכה bracha each day, just to mark each day afresh. תוספות Tosafot
says, more like the גמרא Gemara's comparison to תפילין, tefillin, a ברכה
bracha each time you're going to do a new distinct act. Even
though conceptually it's a process like wearing תפילין tefillin is conceptually an
ongoing process, nevertheless each distinct act gets its own ברכה bracha and
here too by סוכה sukkah every distinct act of going back into
the סוכה sukkah gets its own ברכה. bracha. And that actually of
course is our practice. David, you had a question?
Yeah, it wasn't actually about these conclusions, just the distinction between the
תפילין, tefillin, not only the bathroom, but also you're not allowed to
wear it when you go to sleep. Right. So that would- you'd
have to do that. Right. But with the סוכה, sukkah, you-
right, the sleeping, right, and that is exactly true. Exactly. The whole
idea that סוכה sukkah is really ongoing. There's never a moment you're
not allowed to be in סוכה, sukkah, even sleeping is part of
the מצוה mitzvah of- of being in a סוכה. sukkah. So you
know, so there really nothing interrupts the process of סוכה. sukkah. So
you really understand the idea you make it once in the beginning
of the seven days. Right? So it's really... It really is different
than תפילין, Tefillin, because by תפילין, Tefillin, right, there, you could even
go I would even go further. תפילין, Tefillin, there are moments, even
if conceptually it's a process, there are moments you're not wearing תפילין.
Tefillin. If I took off my תפילין Tefillin for five minutes, I
wasn't wearing it for that five minutes. Whereas by סוכה, Sukkah, even
if I'm not physically in the סוכה Sukkah for the last hour,
I could still be living in the סוכה. Sukkah. Living the סוכה
Sukkah does not mean you're physically present there. I live in my
house. It doesn't mean every moment I'm in my house. So really
by סוכה, Sukkah, the idea that the whole week is an uninterrupted,
whatever you're doing, if you're always going back to your סוכה Sukkah
to eat and to sleep, then whatever you're doing during that week,
the entire time you're living in your סוכה. Sukkah. So you really
understand the power of the idea of making the ברכה Bracha once.
Of course, as we know, if you fail to make a ברכה
Bracha on things, then psychologically they don't feel as much of a
מצוה. Mitzvah. And we have enough of a hard time making living
in the סוכה Sukkah a sense of an ongoing מצוה, Mitzvah, but
at least at a conceptual level... so it's important that we do
make a lot of ברכות Brachos by סוכה. Sukkah. But at least
at a conceptual level, you really you're absolutely correct when you're sleeping...
when sleeping is one of the biggest קיומים Kiyumim of being in
the סוכה. Sukkah. But really whatever you're doing, it's an uninterrupted process.
Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara concludes based on a comparison to תפילין, Tefillin,
which as you point out is not a complete comparison, that we
make a ברכה Bracha multiple times in a סוכה, Sukkah, whether multiple
times means like רש״י Rashi daily, or multiple times means like תוספות
Tosafot says and like is our practice at every discrete act is
when we make the ברכה Bracha by סוכה. Sukkah. Now there's another
question, why do we make the ברכה Bracha only by eating and
not by sleeping? Because here תוספות Tosafot mentions sleeping, but elsewhere תוספות
Tosafot acknowledges that our practice is only to make it by eating
and not by sleeping. Okay, and for us of course we don't
eat and sleep in a סוכה, Sukkah, which is a conversation by
itself. Okay, but let's take a look and maybe that was reinforced
by the idea that we stopped making ברכות Brachos by sleeping in
the סוכה. Sukkah. Which really is quite fascinating how ברכות Brachos influence
our psychological attachment to what's a real מצוה Mitzvah and what's not
a real מצוה. Mitzvah. Yes.
I find it interesting that we're not following the usual הלכתית Halakhic
rule here of יחיד ורבים. Yachid ve-Rabbim.
Well, we're not done, I mean we're doing... I mean there's also
a... oh you mean because of רבי Rebbe and the רבנן? Rabbanan?
Yeah, but always these things are up for discussion. And then there's
also a הלכה כבתראי, Halakha k'vatra'ei, so the later אמוראים Amoraim here
are coming to a certain consensus. Presumably because both אביי Abaye and
רבא, Rava, רבא Rava not by his words but by his actions
wound up implicitly פסקנינג paskening like רבי. Rebbe. רבי. Rebbe. Okay, so
אמר מר זוטרא, Amar Mar Zutra, חזינא ליה לרב פפא, Chazina lei
l'Rav Pappa, I saw רב פפא, Rav Pappa, דכל אימת דמנח תפילין,
de-chol eimas de-manach Tefillin, now we're wrapping up... oh, excuse the pun...
some points about the תפילין. Tefillin. I saw I saw I saw
רב פפא Rav Pappa that every time he would put on תפילין,
Tefillin, מברך, mevarech, he would make the ברכה, Bracha, even multiple times
in a day, and again reinforcing this idea of multiple times. רבנן
דבי רב אשי כל אימת דמשמשי בהו מברכי, Rabbanan d'bei Rav Ashi
chol eimas d'mashmashi behu mevarechi, and this is maybe even more relevant
because it says every time they would feel the תפילין Tefillin they'd
make a ברכה. Bracha. That's like the most relevant because it's one
thing to say you take it off you put it on again,
there's a period you weren't wearing תפילין. Tefillin. Here he's saying even
though they were wearing תפילין Tefillin continuously, every time they like psychologically
reengaged the מצוה, Mitzvah, they just felt their תפילין, Tefillin, they make
a ברכה Bracha again. So that's really... I mean that could be
a lot of ברכות. Brachos. But that really is the most relevant
to סוכה, Sukkah, where we're acknowledging you haven't stopped doing the מצוה,
Mitzvah, you've been doing it continuously, but even so a certain type
of a sort of engagement with it, a sort of reconnecting
to it in a conscious way you'll make a new
ברכה. Bracha. So you understand how that is really very parallel to
סוכה. Sukkah. You could be doing it continuously but there could still
be moments where you're going to make a new ברכה. Bracha. Because
until now as I said by תפילין Tefillin there were really periods
you stop doing תפילין. Tefillin. Here's a case where you were doing
תפילין Tefillin continuously and there would still be multiple opportunities to be
making a ברכה. Bracha. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, מצות לולב כל
שבעה, Mitzvat Lulav kol shiva, the מצוה Mitzvah of לולב Lulav is
all seven days. ורבי יהושע בן לוי אמר יום ראשון, ve-Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi amar yom rishon, only the first day. אמר יום ראשון
מצות לולב מכאן ואילך מצות זקנים, Amar yom rishon Mitzvat Lulav mi-kan
va-eilach Mitzvat zekenim, the first day is the מצוה Mitzvah of לולב,
Lulav, afterwards it's rabbinic. Now what are they debating? Nobody has ever
said there's a biblical מצוה Mitzvah of לולב Lulav on the rest
of the days. So what they're debating is, in this context it's
clear and they're debating when you make the ברכה. Bracha. It's another
way of saying the question, do you make the ברכה Bracha on
לולב Lulav all seven days even when it's rabbinic? Even the other
days after day one when it's rabbinic. So the first position that
says the מצוה Mitzvah is seven days means you make the ברכה
Bracha all seven days. Again, fascinating, the association of making the ברכה
Bracha with fully owning its identity as a מצוה. Mitzvah. So מצות
לולב כל שבעה Mitzvat Lulav kol shiva means you make the ברכה
Bracha all seven days, whereas the other one says, no, only the
first day is biblical, that's the only day you make the ברכה,
Bracha, the rest of the days is rabbinic, you don't make the
ברכה. Bracha. ורבי יצחק אמר, ve-Rabbi Yitzchak amar, and רבי יצחק Rabbi
Yitzchak says, כל יומא מצות זקנים, kol yoma Mitzvat zekenim, so every
day is rabbinic and you don't make a ברכה. Bracha. So every
day? says the גמרא. Gemara. ואפילו יום ראשון? ve-afilu yom rishon? He
would even say the first day? It's only a rabbinic מצוה Mitzvah.
*mitzvah*? וקיימלאן דיום ראשון דאורייתא *ve-kaimlan d'yom rishon d'oraita*, don't we say
that the first day is biblical? So okay, אימא *eima*, no, בר
מיום ראשון *bar mi-yom rishon*. All right, he means it's all rabbinic
after day one. אי הכי היינו דרבי יהושע בן לוי *ee hachi
haynu de-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*? So that's what we just said, the
position that it was biblical the first day and rabbinic the other
days. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אימא רישא וכן אמר Amar
רבי יצחק *eima reisha ve-chen amar Rabbi Yitzchak*. Okay, and רבי יצחק
*Rabbi Yitzchak* also says the same point. So by the way, we
should just take a moment to appreciate that that's a very difficult
read of the ברייתא *Baraita* and the and the simple sense here
is, I mean not the ברייתא *Baraita* sorry, of this Amoraic statement.
And the simple sense of this position of רבי יצחק *Rabbi Yitzchak*
really is that he did not think לולב Lulav *Lulav* was biblical.
Maybe חוץ לארץ *Chutz L'Aretz* he thought לולב Lulav. *Lulav* was only
biblical in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. Maybe he didn't think it
was biblical outside, very shocking position which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* immediately
has to reinterpret. Anyway, we once again have this debate, which is,
do you make the ברכה Berachah. *bracha* on לולב Lulav. *Lulav* on
the other days which are rabbinic, after, on חול המועד Chol HaMoed,
*Chol HaMoed*? So let's take a look. ואף רב Rav סבר כל
שבעה מצות לולב Kol Shiva Mitzvat Lulav. *ve-af Rav savar kol shivah
mitzvat lulav*. Even רב Rav *Rav* holds that the מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah*
of לולב Lulav, *Lulav* is all seven. Again, what it means is
you make the ברכה Berachah, *bracha* all seven days. And how do
you make a ברכה Berachah *bracha* all seven days on something rabbinic?
So now we're shifting from this fascinating לולב Lulav *Lulav* סוכה Sukkah,
*Sukkah* discussion to the לולב Lulav *Lulav* question of making a ברכה
Berachah. *bracha* on something rabbinic. So רב Rav *Rav* also can be
understood to say you make a ברכה Berachah *bracha* even when it's
rabbinic. דאמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב המדליק נר של חנוכה
Chanukah. צריך לברך *d'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav hamadlik ner
shel Chanukah tzarich l'vareich*. When you light חנוכה Chanukah, *Chanukah* candles you
have to make a ברכה Berachah. *bracha*. So רב *Rav* says if
you make a ברכה Berachah *bracha* on חנוכה Chanukah *Chanukah* candles, you
see רב *Rav* is okay with making a מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah* ברכה
bracha, *bracha* on a rabbinic מצוה Mitzvah, *mitzvah*. רבי ירמיה אומר Omer,
*Rabbi Yirmiyah omer*, now that we're mentioning the חנוכה Chanukah *Chanukah* candles
we're going to digress a little bit about that, הרואה נר של
חנוכה Chanukah, צריך לברך *haro'eh ner shel Chanukah tzarich l'vareich*. Even if
you didn't light, you weren't at home and you didn't light חנוכה
*Chanukah* candles, if you see them on the street, you make the
ברכה bracha. *bracha* of, what ברכה *bracha* do you make when you
see them on the street? שעשה נסים *she'asah nissim*, okay, because חנוכה
*Chanukah* and פורים Purim *Purim* are the only two you know sort
of holiday that you make the ברכה *bracha* or מצוה Mitzvah. *mitzvah*
you make the ברכה *bracha* שעשה נסים *she'asah nissim*. Because those are
מצות mitzvos, *mitzvahs* that are, they're both the rabbinic ones and those
are the מצות mitzvos *mitzvahs* where there's heavy focus on publicizing the
miracle, on פרסומי ניסא *pirsumei nisa*. And that's why we make the
ברכה *bracha* of שעשה נסים *she'asah nissim*. Because it's about publicizing. So
even if you didn't actually perform the מצוה Mitzvah. *mitzvah* act, you
just saw somebody who had lit the candles, so you're part of
that act of of it being publicized, you're the receiver of the
message and therefore you also make the ברכה *bracha* of שעשה נסים
*she'asah nissim*. The גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like this, מאי מברך Mevarech,
*mai mivareich*? What is the actual ברכה *bracha*? אמר רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda. *amar Rabbi Yehudah*, יום ראשון *yom rishon*, if you're the lighter
on the first day you make the ברכה *bracha* המדליק מברך שלש
*hamadlik mevareich shalosh*. You make שלש *shalosh*: שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *shehecheyanu*, להדליק נר
*l'hadlik ner*, שעשה נסים *she'asah nissim*, and שהחיינו Shehecheyanu? *shehecheyanu*. הרואה *haro'eh*
and you see it מברך שתים Mevarech Shtayim, *mevareich shtayim*. You say
שעשה נסים *she'asah nissim*, you don't say להדליק *l'hadlik* because you didn't
light, but you say you say שעשה נסים *she'asah nissim* and you
say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *shehecheyanu* because remember שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *shehecheyanu* is encountering the
מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*, not even doing the מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*. So before
we had you encountered it because you were putting your לולב Lulav,
*Lulav* together before it was סוכות Sukkos *Sukkos*. Here you're encountering it,
it is חנוכה *Chanukah*, but you're not doing the act of lighting.
But nevertheless you're encountering the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, so you make the
ברכה *bracha*. Okay, מכאן ואילך *mikan va'eilach* after day one, so you'll
just drop the שהחיינו shehecheyanu *shehecheyanu*. מדליק מברך שתים *madlik mevareich shtayim*,
the lighter says two: להדליק *l'hadlik* and שעשה נסים *she'asah nissim*. ורואה
מברך אחת *ve-ro'eh mevareich achat* which is שעשה נסים *she'asah nissim*. ומאי
מברך *u-mai mevareich*? Now, what actually is the text? Because I've been
filling in the blanks. What actually is the text of the ברכה
*bracha* of the מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* of נר חנוכה *ner Chanukah*? ברוך
אתה ה' אלקינו מלך העולם אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו asher kideshanu bemitzvotav
vetzivanu. להדליק נר של חנוכה *baruch atah Hashem elokeinu melech ha'olam asher
kidishanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu l'hadlik ner shel Chanukah* or נר חנוכה *ner Chanukah*,
different גרסאות *girsa'ot*. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* finally says, okay
it's a rabbinic מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, והיכן צונו *ve-heichan tzivanu*? Where were
we exactly commanded to light חנוכה *Chanukah* candles? מלא תסור *mi-lo tasur*.
It says don't sway from the matters that they will tell you
when you go to adjudicate an issue to the according to the
בית דין הגדול *Beit Din HaGadol*, the כהנים *Kohanim* and the שופט
*Shofet* that are on you know הר הבית *Har HaBayit* אל המקום
אשר יבחר ה' *el hamakom asher yivchar Hashem*, and don't veer from
the matter they tell you. So we're biblically mandated to listen to
the sages and therefore we can say that you God commanded us.
רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman Bar Yitzchak אמר שאל אביך ויגדך
She'al Avicha Veyagedcha. *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar sha'al avicha ve-yageidcha*. Ask
your father and he will tell you, meaning again follow the traditions
and the rulings of the previous generation. So just one brief comment,
there's obviously a lot to say about this about rabbinic authority and
so on but one brief comment: why the look for a different
פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* other than לא תסור Lo Tasur *Lo Tasur*? לא
תסור Lo Tasur *Lo Tasur* is a biblical מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, don't
sway. Why quote this פסוק *pasuk* from you know that's more poetic
and not really mandate you must listen etc.? So the point is
because לא תסור *Lo Tasur* is much more about the rabbi's role
in interpreting biblical מצות mitzvos. *mitzvot*. By the debate what is this
biblical מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, do I have to do this for שבת
Shabbat *Shabbos*, do I do that for שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*, and you
go to the sages and they will tell you you know how
to understand God's word. That's the case in the תורה Torah, *Torah*
of לא תסור *Lo Tasur* and ועשית על פי התורה אשר יורוך
*ve-asita al pi hatorah asher yorucha*, following them not swaying is in
there. their interpretive capacity. In something of establishing new practices, that's not
really what the פסוק of לא תסור is talking about. So that's
why the גמרא Gemara here seeks another פסוק of שאל אביך ויגדך.
Just listen to your parents. Just listen, just follow the practices that
were established even if it's not in their interpretive role, even if
it's in establishing new practices. Okay, so that's just appreciating the two
פסוקים. Pesukim. The other interesting thing to say since we're right in
the aftermath of פורים Purim, is that the גמרא Gemara, doesn't ask
this question by מגילה, Megillah, it only asks it by חנוכה. But
the גמרא, Gemara why not? Same issue by פורים, Purim. a new
מצוה. mitzvah But the גמרא Gemara asks another question by פורים. Purim
You know what the question the גמרא Gemara. asks by פורים Purim
is?
Is it הלל? Hallel?
No, so yes, but that's not my point. My point is the
question it asks by פורים Purim is whether אסתר Esther was given
ברוח הקודש Beruach Hakodesh and how do we know that אסתר Esther
is one of the books of תנ"ך Tanakh and whether אסתר Esther
is מטמא את הידיים Metameh Et Hayadayim and the famous מדרש, Midrash,
אסתר Esther writes to the חכמים, Chachamim, כתבוני לדורות, Kitvuni Ledorot, which
is a way of saying include me in תנ"ך? Tanakh? Because once
אסתר Esther got to be in תנ"ך, Tanakh, there's no problem of
saying וציוונו. Vetzivanu. Why? Because the writing, the מצוה mitzvah. of reading
the מגילה Megillah is in the מגילה. Megillah. So if you can
make the מגילה Megillah part of תנ"ך, Tanakh, so the idea that
this is coming from God, okay, not from the תורה, Torah? from
תנ"ך, Tanakh, but it's coming from God, so you can say וציוונו.
Vetzivanu. So by אסתר, Esther, the question is getting the book of
the מגילה Megillah in תנ"ך, Tanakh, whereas by here where it was
never about Maccabees being in תנ"ך, Tanakh, Christians have it in their
Bible, we don't, you had to directly address the question of where
is the authority to say וציוונו Vetzivanu and it quotes this idea
of לא תסור and so on. So this is the idea that
by a Rabbinic מצוה you can say וציוונו Vetzivanu and since we
say that by חנוכה, says the גמרא, Gemara we would actually, we
would say it by לולב Lulav, as well. And now the גמרא
Gemara just ends that point by saying, wait a minute, רב נחמן
בר יצחק Rav Nachman Bar Yitzchak מתני לה בהדיא. Matni Lah Behedya.
רב נחמן בר יצחק teaches it explicitly, not that we can infer
from what רב says by חנוכה to what רב would say by
לולב. lulav, No, explicitly רב said it by לולב. lulav אמר רב,
כל שבעה מצות mitzvos, לולב. lulav, The whole seven days is the
מצוה, which means in this context the whole seven days you are
making the ברכה. So what is our conclusion? By לולב, the conclusion
is yes, it's Rabbinic on חול המועד, but we make ברכת המצוה
Birchat HaMitzvah on Rabbinic מצוות, Mitzvot, so we make לולב every day.
סוכה, Sukkah yes, it's a continuous process. There's a nice logic to
make it once, but following this model of תפילין, Tefillin, particularly the
model that every time you touch the תפילין Tefillin you make a
ברכה, that's not what we do, but anyway, following the model of
תפילין, Tefillin, although it's a continuous process, you do make the ברכה
of סוכה Sukkah as well during the course of the seven days.
According to רש"י, Rashi, it's once a day; according to תוספות, Tosafot,
which is our practice, it's every time discrete act and every time
you re-enter the סוכה Sukkah, to eat in the סוכה, Sukkah you
make a new ברכה. Yes, do you have a question?
Is it more compelling to say that this סוגיא Sugya is primary
location is in שבת and brought here as opposed to the other
way around?
I don't know.
In other words, there's links both ways, right?
Yeah, it is true, it is true.
In other words, here it's contextual, there it's במה מדליקין. Bameh Madlikin.
Right, right, so
in other words, probably,
yeah, could very well be, yeah, yeah, could very well be. Right,
what type of grouping is the more natural grouping is an interesting
question, but yeah. All right, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, העושה סוכה לעצמו, Ha'oseh
Sukkah Le'atzmo, אומר ברוך שהחיינו וקימנו, Omer Baruch Shehecheyanu Vekiyimanu, נכנס לישב
בה, Nichnas Leyashev Bah, אומר ברוך אשר קדשנו במצותיו. Omer Baruch Asher
Kiddeshanu Bemitzvotav. So now we're going back to what we said before.
Now, however, we establish, so that's the idea of שהחיינו shehecheyanu and
making a ברכה when you go in and we had discussed how
many times you make the ברכה. Now,
היתה עשויה ועומדת, Hayetah Asuyah Ve'omedet, let's say your סוכה Sukkah. was
pre-built, okay?
When am I going to make a שהחיינו? shehecheyanu I didn't build
the סוכה. Sukkah, So אם יכול לחדש בה דבר, Im Yachol Lechadesh
Bah Davar, if you can add something new to your סוכה, Sukkah,
מברך, then do something new, put up some new decorations or put
up a little more סכך, Sechach, and that'll allow you to make
the ברכה of שהחיינו shehecheyanu on engaging in the מצוה. ואם לאו,
Ve'im Lav, and if you didn't do anything to really make the,
make the סוכה, Sukkah, וכשיכנס לישב בה, Uchesheyikanes Leyashev Bah, so fine,
so then when you finally actually do the act, then מברך שתים,
you make both ברכות. Berachot. And again, this is what we do.
Although we could in theory make שהחיינו shehecheyanu when we're putting together
the לולב or when we're putting up our סוכה, Sukkah. we don't
do it at the earliest stages, we do them when we're actually
doing the מצוה. אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Assi, says רב אסי,
Rav Assi, חזינא ליה לרב כהנא, Chazina Leh LeRav Kahana, I saw
רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, דקאמר להו לכולהו אכסא דקידושא. Dekamar Lehu Lekulhu
Akasa Dekiddusha. He waited saying all of it over קידוש. Kiddush. And
this is what we do, right? Because actually, it's true by the
לולב, we do it when you're sitting, when you're taking the לולב,
but actually it's important to appreciate that there's a, the another stage
in the גמרא. Gemara Because the גמרא is talking about the סוכה.
Sukkah Well, the סוכה Sukkah, starts at the first night. So the
גמרא first said is if you didn't make it when you put
together the סוכה, Sukkah. make it when you first walk into the
סוכה. Sukkah Now, that we don't do that. We wait for סוכה
Sukkah. till we're actually making קידוש. Kiddush. Okay, so there's all these
stages. First, make it when you're putting together the סוכה. Sukkah Oh,
you didn't do that? Do something new and add something to the
סוכה sukkah. and then make it. Oh, you didn't do that? It's
already focused, it's you're coming home from שול, shul, make it as
soon as you walk into the סוכה. sukkah, And then finally it
says, you know what, we waited this long, we might as well
just wrap it all up into the קידוש. kiddush. And that's what
the גמרא says. And that is our practice. Again, and that also
sounds like it's not a בדיעבד. bedi'eved. Like he basically figured as
long as I'm going to, you know, have to make it on
the סוכה, sukkah. might as well incorporate it all into the קידוש.
kiddush. And as we said, the שהחיינו shehecheyanu on the קידוש kiddush
winds up doing double duty. It's a שהחיינו shehecheyanu for the יום
טוב yontif and it's a שהחיינו for סוכה. sukkah. By לולב, we
do it at the moment we're about to do the מצוה.
If a person did it, they made a שהחיינו when they were
putting together their סוכה. sukkah Right. Is it a הלכה halachic issue,
it's a מנהג minhag issue of how we do it? Look, the
irony is, or the funny thing is, why we say the שהחיינו
after the אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו. asher kideshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu. Because you
could say that's a הפסק. hefsek. Since in theory the שהחיינו could
have been said earlier, even if we want to wait and do
it at the time of doing the מצוה, right, say it before
you say the ברכת המצוה, birchas hamitzvah, you know, because the שהחיינו
idea began earlier. So it's actually quite fascinating that once we're actually
waiting to the performance, we completely integrate it into the performance and
we actually do it even after the
אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו. Okay, so now the גמרא continues.
Where were we? תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. היו לפניו מצות הרבה. Hayu
lefanav mitzvos harbeh. Now we're talking about ברכות brachos on מצות, we'll
talk a little bit more generally. You have many מצות to do.
רש"י Rashi says let's say taking your לולב and sitting in your
סוכה sukkah and putting on תפילין tefillin and putting on ציצית. tzitzis.
You wake up סוכות morning and you want to do all four
of these מצות. אומר, ברוך אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על המצות. Baruch
asher kideshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu al hamitzvos. So you save yourself from making
four separate ברכות, brachos, one big ברכה, על המצות. al hamitzvos. רבי
יהודה אומר מברך על כל אחת ואחת בפני עצמה. Rabbi Yehuda omer
mevarech al kol achas ve'achas bifnei atzmah. No, let's not have cheat
any one out of its unique ברכה. You make the separate one
on each one. אמר רבי זירא ואיתימא רבי חנינא בר פפא הלכתא
כרבי יהודה. Amar Rabbi Zeira ve'isayma Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa hilchesa keRabbi
Yehuda. We rule like
רבי יהודה. ואמר רבי זירא, Ve'amar Rabbi Zeira, that you make it
on each one. ואמר רבי זירא ואיתימא רבי חנינא בר פפא מאי
טעמא דרבי יהודה? Ve'amar Rabbi Zeira ve'isayma Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa mai
ta'ama deRabbi Yehuda? What's the logic behind this? Why not just lump
them all together? דכתיב, Dechesiv, right, a generic. ברוך ה' יום יום,
Baruch Hashem yom yom, Blessed God every day. וכי ביום מברכין אותו
ובלילה אין מברכין אותו? Vechi bayom mevorchin oso belailah ein mevorchin oso?
What, maybe you only bless him in the daytime not at night?
What it mean every day? אלא בא לומר לך, Ella ba lomar
lach, it's telling you בכל יום ויום תן לו מעין ברכותיו. bechol
yom vayom ten lo mi'ein birchosav. Every day you should bless God
and acknowledge the unique gifts of that day. Okay, now you could
just say that at an experiential level, right? You wake up today
and the birds are chirping, so you, oh my God, it's so
beautiful, you thank God for the chirping birds. You wake up tomorrow
and I don't know, and it's raining and it's windy, you thank
God for the rain and the wind. You know, every day you
acknowledge. But of course we're talking in the more technical liturgical context
where it's not so free-form. So what does it mean thank God
for the unique blessings every day? It means on ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh you mention ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, on חנוכה you mention חנוכה,
you know, on פורים Purim. you mention פורים. Every day you insert
into the תפילה, tefillah, not every day because a lot of days
are, don't have that distinct quality to them in that sort of
technical sense. But every day you sort of bring in, if there's
something distinct, you mention what's distinct about that day.
הכא נמי, Hacha nami, it's the same way it's true about the
day, here too בכל דבר ודבר תן לו מעין ברכותיו. bechol davar
vedavar ten lo mi'ein birchosav. If you're doing multiple מצות, every מצוה
you should acknowledge the distinct blessing of that of being given this
מצוה. The מצוה of סוכה is a different way in which God
has blessed us and sanctified us than the מצוה of לולב, than
the מצוה of טלית, tallis, than the מצוה of תפילין. tefillin. You
don't want to take away the distinct nature because it also undermines,
you know, we would say, I would say at the experiential level,
it undermines, you know, our relationship to it as, you know, as
a special מצוה. In the sort of at the theological level in
terms of thanking God, you know, we're taking away some distinctive way
of acknowledging, in a distinct way of giving thanks and of blessing
God. Okay, ואמר רבי זירא ואיתימא רבי חנינא בר פפא בוא וראה
שלא כמדת הקדוש ברוך הוא מדת בשר ודם. Ve'amar Rabbi Zeira ve'isayma
Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa bo re'eh shelo kemiddas hakadosh baruch hu middas
basar vadam. Come see that God's ways are not the ways of
human beings. Right? These are all connected because it's the same person
saying it. מדת בשר ודם, Middas basar vadam, the way of human
beings, flesh and blood, כלי ריקן מחזיק, kli reikan machazik,
an empty vessel can hold new content. מלא אינו מחזיק, Malei eino
machazik, a full vessel cannot hold any new content. אבל מדת הקדוש
ברוך הוא, Aval middas hakadosh baruch hu, but the way of God
is not this way. מלא מחזיק, Malei machazik, if it's full it'll
be able to hold better. ריקן אינו מחזיק, Reikan eino machazik, if
it's empty it won't be able to hold. שנאמר והיה אם שמוע
תשמע, Shene'emar vehayah im shamoa tishma, it'll be if you surely listen
to what God says. אם שמוע, Im shamoa, if you've already listened
before, תשמע, tishma, you'll be able to hear more. רש"י Rashi says,
you'll, you know, you'll have trained yourself to the whole, you know,
to the disposition of paying attention. Rashi says you'll have trained yourself
to the whole disposition of paying attention and listening and the more
you've listened before the more you'll continue to listen in the future.
ואם לאו Veim lav and if you haven't trained yourself to listen.
Oh, I keep myself—what was that movie, was it that—that what's-his-name was
in, was it the Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind? Right. So
I keep my mind a total blank. So it doesn't mean that
it makes it easier to absorb things. If you haven't trained yourself
to listen before, לא תשמע, Lo tishma, you will not succeed in
listening in the future. Okay, so Rashi talks, by the way, about
the issue of a disposition to be able to listen and to
pay attention and to focus. You could also, by the way, talk
about the idea of association of ideas. Right, the more ideas that
you have in your head, then when you bring in a new
idea, in a way because it makes connections and associates with ideas
that are already there, in ways you can hold on to it
better than if you're taking in an idea that has no context
and no other idea to associate with. This is until you get
to be—until you get to be older, then you start just forgetting
everything.
What an ordinary ancient way of framing
Hebraic constructivist theory. Right. You only understand things in context of other
things you
already have something of understanding that you make a connection to. Right.
Right. It's completely the most contemporary educational development.
Exactly. So it's very powerful. And again, Rashi talks about a disposition,
but I would say, as David said, that it has to do
just about the ability to
comprehend because you can associate it with ideas you've already heard. Okay.
ואם לאו לא תשמע. Veim lav lo tishma. דבר אחר, Davar acher,
another way of saying it, אם שמוע בישן תשמע בחדש. Im shamoa
bayashan tishma bachadash. If you heard the old, you'll be able to
hear new. But then the next verse says, ואם יפנה לבבך ולא
תשמע, Veim yifneh levavecha velo tishma, if your heart turns away and
you don't hear. So the way it's reading it, if your heart
turned away, if you stopped paying attention, then שוב לא תשמע, Shuv
lo tishma, you will not hear again. Now, what does this mean
דבר אחר? Davar acher? Isn't this saying the same thing? So Rashi
says this last point is about doing
חזרה. Chazarah. The first point was, the more you've learned in general,
the more it'll be—you'll gain that disposition of paying attention and learning
in context, the more you'll be able to learn. The next point
is, if you go back to review what you've learned before, then
it'll be also easier to continue and to absorb new things. But
if you never review, then it basically is in one ear out
the other and you don't get to—and then it's—then it's—does not become
possible to learn. Now, the funny thing, by the way, is that
this says God's way is not the way of human beings. What's
God's way? We're the ones that are doing the learning. Is it
a specific point it's making about תורה? Torah? That this is about
תורה? Torah You know, that תורה has this ability? It doesn't seem
so, it seems that this is a universal reality. So it seems
that God's way is about the making of the vessel. We make
a cup and the cup only contains things when it's open, empty.
It doesn't contain things when it's full. God makes the human being
and the human mind, that's God's way, how He's made us, you
know, we are the containers that God has made. And we're a
type of a container that the more we're filled, the more we're
able to be filled, and if it's empty, then it does not
get filled.
Okay. So it's whatever. I didn't think it pays to begin the
next topic, so we're a bit behind, but we will try to
catch up here on שבת.
All right. Okay.